[The Age of Awakening]
[觉醒年代]
[Episode One]
[第一集]
World War I
第一次世界大战
entered its second year of unprecedented tragedy.
进入空前惨烈的第二年
While Germany was distracted in the European theatre,
趁德国在欧洲战场分身乏术
Japan stepped up its expansion in China.
日本加紧了在中国的扩张
During the period
在此前后
of the Second Revolution's failure,
自二次革命失败
Sun Yat-sen and others were forced into exile overseas.
孙中山等被迫流亡海外
Bourgeois revolutionaries
资产阶级革命派
were unable to carry out the anti-imperialist and anti-feudal struggle to the end.
无力把反帝反封建的斗争进行到底
Domestic political chaos,
国内政局混乱
the suffering of the people,
人民痛苦不堪
internal trouble and foreign aggression.
内忧外患
China was once again thrown into a tumultuous situation.
再次将中国抛入风雨飘摇之中
Mr. President,
大总统
Japanese diplomat Hioki Eki has sent an ultimatum
日本公使日置益送来最后通
to be answered within forty-eight hours.
限四十八小时内答复
What does the ultimatum say?
最后通 怎么说
[Yuan Shikai, President of the Republic of China]
[袁世凯 中华民国总统]
If the Twenty-One Demands
如不在限定时间内
[Liang Shiyi, styled Yifu, Secretary General of the Presidential Office of the Republic of China]
[梁士诒 字 翼夫 中华民国总统府秘书长]
are not accepted within the timeframe,
接受二十一条
then Japan will take necessary measures.
日本 必将采取必要之手段
[Cao Rulin, styled Runtian, Vice Minister of Foreign Affairs of the Republic of China]
[曹汝霖 字 润田 中华民国外交部次长]
What does he want?
他想怎么着
Hioki Eki said
日置益说
Japan is to take over Shandong in the northeast.
日本将以东北模式接管山东
Japanese... They still want us dead.
日本人 亡我之心不死啊
This afternoon, the Ministry of War reported
下午军部报告说
that Japanese naval formations
日本的海军编队
are heading for our southeast coast.
有驶往我东南沿海之迹象
What?
怎么着
Does he still want a Jiawu War (=First Sino-Japanese War)?
他还想来场甲午大战吗
Make no mistake.
不要搞错了
I am Yuan Shikai,
我是袁世凯
not Li Hongzhang.
不是李鸿章
For a long time, there have been discussions in Japan
日本国内早有典论
advocating for Japanese intervention
主张日本
in our country's Yangtze River basin as soon as possible.
尽快介入我国长江流域活动
Stupid... Stupid...
窝囊 窝囊啊
You didn't tell Hioki Eki that
你没有跟日置益说
it's not that I, Yuan Shikai, who disagreed with the Twenty-One Demands.
不是我袁世凯不同意二十一条
It's the people who are rebelling so much.
是民众反抗得厉害
It was them who hid Sun Yat-sen and Huang Xing in Japan.
他们把孙中山 黄兴藏在日本
Didn't I say we should respect public opinion?
不是也说要尊重民意吗
Mr. President, our appeal has worked.
大总统这招奏效了
The Japanese agree that the articles in Section 5
日本人同意第五项中各条
can be discussed later.
可以日后商量
But... the treaty must be signed immediately.
但是 条约必须马上就签
How does your Ministry of Foreign Affairs respond?
你们外交部有什么对策
The Ministry of Foreign Affairs obeys the orders of the President.
外交部唯大总统命是从
How cunning.
滑头
Then accept the Japanese terms.
那就接受日本人的条件吧
Now Sun Yat-sen, Huang Xing and the others will make trouble again.
这下孙中山黄兴他们又要闹事了
All these people have gone overseas.
这些人都跑外面去了
It won't be a big deal.
成不了大气候
Right.
对了
Runtian, tell the Japanese
润田啊 你跟日本人说
the treaty will be signed,
字可以签
but Section 5 of the Demands will not be accepted.
但第五部分那几条不能同意
This is the bottom line.
这个是底线
I gave him face,
我给他脸
he should also give me some.
他也得给我留个台阶啊
Understood, Mr. President.
谨遵大总统训示
What is the deadline for the Japanese?
几号是日本人的最后期限
Nine days.
九号
Then wait until the night of the ninth day
那就等到九号晚上
to inform the Japanese.
再通告日本人
Extra! Extra!
看号外 看号外
Today's extra is very strange!
今天的号外真叫怪
President Yuan Shikai
大总统 袁世凯
is selling out the country!
把祖宗的家业往外卖
The wastrel, sells, sells, sells!
这个败家子 卖卖卖
His support is not afraid to rise up,
腰杆子不敢直起来
but the common masses do not agree
可国人百姓不答应
to be angry and not fight!
气都不打一处来
Look at this woman! So angry, she steps on the extra!
看这位儿 气得直把号外踩
Look at this man! So angry, he breaks his crutch!
看这位爷 气得戳折手中拐
9 May 1915
一九一五年五月九日
By order of Yuan Shikai,
袁世凯下令
an agreement is signed with Japan,
同意与日本签订
the national humiliation of the Twenty-One Demands.
丧权辱国的二十一条
According to this treaty,
根据这个条约
China recognizes Japan's inheritence of
中国承认日本继承
all German rights and interests in Shandong.
德国在山东的一切权益
Japan in southern Manchuria and eastern Mongolia in China
日本在中国南满和蒙古东部
will enjoy special rights.
享有特殊权利
Japan will get in China
日本获得在中国
various railway construction rights, and so on.
多条铁路建筑权等等
The Beiyang government's treasonous acts
北洋政府的卖国行径
were strongly opposed by the nation.
遭到全国民众的强烈反对
All major cities in China,
全国各大城市
like Beijing, Guangzhou, Wuhan,
如北京广州武汉
Qingdao, and other places
青岛等地
all held huge demonstrations.
都举行了声势浩大的示威游行
Shanghai dockers went on strike
上海码头工人举行黑工
announcing a boycott of Japanese goods.
宣布抵制日货
Workers in Hankow, Zhenjiang, Hanyang, Changsha,
汉口 镇江 汉阳长沙
Fuzhou and other places
福州等地的工人
held various protests one after another.
相继举行各种抗议活动
Refusing to recognise the Twenty-One Demands
拒不承认二十一条
and vowing to avenge national humiliation
誓雪国耻
demonstrate a strong anti-imperialist stance
表现出坚定的反帝立场
and a strong patriotic passion.
和强烈的爱国热情
Sun Yat-sen, Huang Xing and others in exile overseas
流亡海外的孙中山黄兴等人
call for revolutionaries to return to China to oppose Yuan.
呼呼革命者回国倒袁
[Waseda University, Japan]
[日本早稻田大学]
Come and see this!
你们快来看
Latest news from home!
国内最新的消息
Shameless! Insane!
无耻至极 丧心病狂
[Li Dazhao, styled Shouchang, Student at Waseda University]
[李大钊 字 守常 日本早稻田大学学生]
We have been fighting for so long,
我们斗争了这么久
but this is the result.
得到的却是如此结果
[Gao Yihan, Student at Waseda University]
[高一涵 日本早稻田大学学生]
Do we really have no way out?
难道我们真的无路可走了吗
This kind of big event
此等大事
is not something you and I can control.
不是你我能左右得了的
Let's take it easy, let's eat first.
你们别着急 先把饭吃了
When the country's in trouble, there is no time to eat.
国难当头 没心思吃饭
You say you vow to fight back for the country,
誓当与国共患难
how... how can you still eat?
这这 这你怎么还吃得下饭
I can't do without eating!
不吃饭也不行啊
Students! Countrymen!
同学们 同胞们
Heaven kills, the war clouds fly.
天发杀机 战云四飞
The Wa people seize their chance, and force our Xiayu (=Chinese territory).
倭族乘机 逼我夏宇
Students in Japan, detained in an exotic land.
留日学子 羁身异域
Looking back at Shenzhou, facing the sky sorrowful and enraged!
回望神州 仰天悲愤
Now that our country has fallen and our people have died,
既然已经到了国亡人死之际
there is no longer any fear to speak out.
便再无投鼠忌器之顾虑
We should have the determination to press ahead.
我们应该有破釜沉舟之决心
The arch-usurper Yuan Shikai
窃国大盗袁世凯
wants to become emperor and restore the imperial system.
恢复帝制想要当皇帝
The Republic of China is in danger!
中华民国危在旦夕了
The traitor Yuan Shikai
卖国贼袁世凯
has signed the Twenty-One Demands.
已经签订了二十一条
The Chinese nation is in danger!
中华民族危在旦夕了
Countrymen, the Republic is dying.
同胞们 共和就要死了
Qingdao is about to be lost.
青岛就要丢了
Countrymen, what do you say?
同胞们 你们说怎么办
Return home! Return home!
回国 回国
Overthrow Yuan! Return home!
倒袁 回国
Return home!
回国
Overthrow Yuan!
倒袁
Okay, stop yelling.
行了 别喊了
It's up to you guys to overthrow Yuan.
就凭你们啊 还倒袁
Don't make trouble for the country.
别给国家捣乱了
What did you say?
你说什么呢
Zhang Fengzai,
张丰载
now that the country is in trouble and the Republic is dying,
如今国难当头 共和将死
you're all being a bit eccentric here.
你们几个在这里阴阳怪气的
Are you still Chinese?
你们还是中国人吗
Do you have any patriotism left in you?
还有没有一点爱国之心
That's right! Are you Chinese?!
就是 是中国人吗
China has been in this state
中国现在这个样子
for much more than a day or two.
已经不是一天两天了
Can you save the country like this?
就凭你们这样能救国吗
It's all because of you apathetic people!
都是因为你们这些麻木之人
China is falling into a ditch that way!
中国才会沧落到如此田地
Yeah! It is because of you!
对 就是因为你们
Because of us?
因为我们
We won't go along with this accusation.
这个罪名我们可真担不起啊
If it weren't for those stupid revolutionaries.
若不是那些愚蠢的革命党
Had they not wanted to copy the American republican system,
非要照搬什么美利坚的共和制度
China would have been a constitutional monarchy.
中国早就走上了君主立宪的道路
It wouldn't have turned out to be
万不会演变成
the grotesque situation we find ourselves in today.
今天这不伦不类的局面
Yuan Shikai's attempt to introduce a constitutional monarchy
如今袁世凯力图实行君主立宪
was a real return to the correct path.
才是真正回归了正轨
This is the way to save China.
这才是中国的救亡之策
The foundation of prosperity.
富强之本
Nonsense!
胡说八道
Ridiculous! Ridiculous!
荒诊至极 荒诊至极
The idea of a democratic republic
民主共和的思想
is already well established.
早就已经深入人心了
Aren't you driving backwards in history?
你这不是开历史的倒车吗
Yeah! That's right! Driving backwards!
对 没错 就是要开倒车
We are the ones driving backwards in history?
究竟是我等开历史倒车
Or is it you revolutionaries?
还是你们这些革命党
Ignoring China's national conditions!
不顾中国国情一意孤行
Students! Countrymen!
同学们 同胞们
Kang Youwei has long said
康有为先生早就说过
a revolution is not a good thing for a country.
革命非一国之善事
The French Revolution,
法国革命
eighty years of turmoil and bloodshed of millions.
大乱八十年流血数百万
Furthermore, the Chinese people are not yet open-minded.
再者 中国民智未开呀
In this case,
如此情况下
the forced imposition of a republican system
强行推行共和制度
will be like duckweed floating on water, with no roots!
必将如那水上浮萍 无处生根
Zhang Fengzai, what you just said
张丰载 你刚才所说的话
is absolutely absurd!
实乃荒谬
Kang Youwei's words
康有为的话
have been refuted by many revolutionary martyrs.
很多革命先烈早已经驳斤过了
The revolution will certainly shed blood.
革命固然会流血
But I would like to ask you,
但是我想请问你
will the constitutional monarchy, also not shed blood?
君主立宪 便不会流血了吗
Right!
对
[Zhang Shizhao, styled Xingyan, famous social activist forced into exile in Japan for his participation in the "Second Revolution" against Yuan Shikai]
[章士钊 字 行严 著名社会活动家因参加讨伐袁世凯的"二次革命"被迫流亡日本]
Yeah! That's right!
对呀 就是 说啊
Britain, Austria, Germany, Italy.
英 奥 德 意
Which country has not experienced
哪一个国家不是经历了
many changes
多少次的变革
and made great sacrifices
付出了巨大的牺牲
before it has achieved real social progress?
才获得了社会真正的进步
Another thing I want to ask you is,
另外我想问你一句
what did you just say?
你刚才说什么
Our country's people are not yet open-minded?
我们这个国家民智未开呀
That's demonstrably false!
实乃大谬
Since the Xinhai Revolution,
辛亥革命以来
the entire population's thinking
整个民众的思想
has already undergone earth-shaking changes.
早已经得到了翻天覆地的变化
Judging from the unanimous rejection of Yuan at home and abroad,
从海内外齐声倒袁这个现象来看
this is hard evidence.
便是铁证
The more the nation is in peril,
越是在民族危亡之时
the more it should call people's consciousness
就越应该唤起民众的觉悟
and invigorate the national spirit.
振作民族精神
And if the idea of republicanism
而且如果要把共和的思想
is to be instilled in the people,
灌输给民众
it is necessary to overthrow the feudal ideology.
则必须推翻封建的思想
Zhang Fengzai, those who go against the tide of history
张丰载 逆历史潮流者
will be drowned by the torrent of the times.
必被时代的洪流所没
For the love of country,
我们为了爱国
we must save our country. Overthrow Yuan.
必须要救国 倒袁
For our Chinese nation,
我们为了我们的中华民族
we must save our country. Overthrow Yuan!
更必须要救国 倒袁
Save the country! Overthrow Yuan!
救国 倒袁
Well said!
说得好
Mr. Xingyan. Mr. Xingyan.
行严先生 行严先生
Hello students.
同学们好
Shouchang's words
守常的话
were well-reasoned, authentic,
有理有据 发自肺府
passionate, engaging.
慷慨激昂 直指人心
Excellent.
太好了
Zhongfu, what do you think?
仲甫啊 你觉得呢
Zhongfu? Chen Duxiu?
仲甫 陈独秀
It's Chen Duxiu!
他就是陈独秀
Chen Duxiu!
陈独秀
Is it Chen Duxiu?
陈独秀吗
Why does he look like that?
他怎么这个样子啊
[Chen Duxiu, styled Zhongfu, famous revolutionary forced into exile in Japan for his participation in the "Second Revolution" against Yuan Shikai]
[陈独秀 字 仲甫 著名革命家因参加讨伐袁世凯的"二次革命"被迫流亡日本]
Could it be Chen Duxiu?
难道是陈独秀
It can't be.
不像啊
As you said,
如你所言
he is a very knowledgeable young man.
是个见识极高的青年
Chen Duxiu.
陈独秀
Why are you eating here?
怎么在这儿吃上了
I was just passing by
我正好路过
seeing them bickering.
看见他们吵吵闹闹的
No one was eating.
谁都不吃饭
Food should not be wasted at any time.
任何时候都不能浪费粮食
It's shameful to waste food
浪费粮食是可耻的
What time is it? You're still eating here?
什么时候了你还在这儿吃
Are you Chen Duxiu?
你是陈独秀吗
I am, yes.
我是 对
He really is!
他真的是啊
I am Chen Duxiu.
我是陈独秀
He is! He's Chen Duxiu!
他是 他是陈独秀
Quiet, everyone!
大家请安静
Quiet!
请安静
Since Mr. Zhongfu is here,
既然仲甫先生在这儿
we would like to ask you,
我们想请问您
what do you think should be done to save China?
您觉得该如何救这个中国
I think that
我倒觉得
such a country is hopeless.
这样的国 无可救药
What did you say?
你说什么
Are you Chinese? How can you say that?
是中国人吗你怎么能这么说
Chen Duxiu. Are you talking about people?
陈独秀 你说的是人话吗
Simply shameless!
简直是无耻
Shameless!
无耻
What are you doing?
干什么你
You've gone too far!
过分了啊
Mr. Zhongfu, what you just said,
仲甫先生 您刚才所说的
do you really believe that?
真是内心所想
Yes, of course.
那当然是
But yeah, I meant to say...
不过啊 我是想说
You see?!
你们看到了吧
Students! You have seen it!
同学们 你们看到了吧
This is what you call a revolutionary!
这就是你们所谓的革命党
A great revolutionary!
大革命家
Do you know what he said?
知道他说过什么话吗
He said he didn't care for his country's subjugation!
他说亡国无所惜
What else?
还说什么
What's terrible of being a slave to a subjugated country?
亡国为奴 何事可怖
Where is the love for a country of a brutalized people?
残民之国 爱之也何居
This is the real traitor! A hanjian!
这才是真正的卖国贼 大汉奸
Traitor! Hanjian!
卖国贼 大汉奸
Hanjian!
大汉奸
Get out of the way!
让开
Don't do it!
不要动手
Let's just talk!
有话好好说
Stop!
住手
Don't do it!
不要动手 走
Mr. Zhongfu, go!
不要动手
Let's just talk! Don't do it!
有话好好说 不要动手
Come on, this way!
走这边儿
Don't do it, people, don't do it!
不要动手 大家不要动手
Listen to me for a moment!
听我说几句
Mr. Xingyan has a message for everyone!
行严先生有话对大家说
Come on, everyone, let me tell you something!
来 大家听我说两句
Come on, come on!
来 都过来来
Alright.
好了
Alright, alright, no one is following.
好了好了 没人追了
Take a break, take a break.
歇会儿歇会儿
Not like Chen Duxiu, right?
不像陈独秀是吧
I just imagined
就是跟我想象当中的
something a little different.
有点不太一样
So what do you imagine it should be like?
那你想象的应该是什么样
Are you okay?
您没事吧
I apologise for the situation.
真抱歉 遇着这种情况
It's okay, I've seen a lot of these.
没关系 这种场面我见多了
Your article
您的那篇
"Self Consciousness on Patriotism", I've read it.
《爱国心与自觉心》 的文章我看了
But there are many doubts and unanswered questions.
但是有诸多的疑虑和不解
I would like to ask you some, is that okay?
我想跟您请教一下行吗
I know that you, Li Dazhao, are from Hebei.
我知道 你李大钊是河北人
Yanzhao is full of generous and sorrowful people, they insist endlessly.
燕赵多慷概悲歌之士 认死理儿
But now in China
但是现在中国
there is a shortage of real men who insist endlessly.
就缺认死理儿的真汉子
Ask.
问
You said that patriotism should have a position,
您说 爱国要有立场
and not, under the banner of patriotism,
不能打着爱国的旗号
be one of Yuan Shikai's obedient subjects.
甘愿去当袁世凯的顺民
Then according to you,
那按您的意思来说
as long as Yuan Shikai is in power,
只要是袁世凯当政
people should not be patriotic.
大家就不要爱国了
You stubborn man, you misunderstood.
认死理儿的汉子 你误会了
I meant to say,
我的意思是说
patriotism should have a position,
爱国要有立场
and patriotism should not be confused
不能把爱国跟效忠袁世凯
with loyalty to Yuan Shikai,
混同起来
under the banner of patriotism,
打着爱国的旗号
covering up Yuan Shikai's usurp of state power.
来掩饰袁世凯的窃国行为
This is similar to what you just said,
这跟你刚刚的言论
is it not?
不是相符的吗
Then Yuan Shikai
那袁世凯
keeps saying that he represents the country,
口口声声说他就代表国家
he is confusing different concepts.
他是在混淆概念
If patriotism has no position,
如果爱国没有立场
then we simply have no reason
那我们根本就没有理由
to defeat Yuan Shikai.
来打倒袁世凯
I completely agree.
我深以为然
I think the first priority today is
我认为当今的第一要务
to inspire the people to be truly patriotic.
是启发民众真正的爱国心
Right now, China is being divided up by the Western powers.
眼下中国正在被西方列强所瓜分
If everyone is not patriotic,
如果大家都不爱国的话
then the country will die.
那这个国家就亡了
Shouchang, I ask you,
守常我问你
What did the Western powers rely on to carve up China?
西方列强瓜分中国靠的是什么
Gunboats.
船坚炮利啊
No.
非也
You are talking about the Opium War and naval failure of the Jiawu War.
你说的那是鸦片战争和甲午海事
Now the powers are dividing China by borrowing money.
现在列强瓜分中国靠的是借债
The Chinese government
中国政府
borrows foreign debt from Western countries every year,
每年向西方各国借的外债
accounting for more than half of the treasury's revenue
占国库收入的一半以上
in a country without productivity.
一个没有生产力的国家
Only by relying on the national tax railway as collateral
只能靠以国税铁路为抵押
can we borrow money to maintain political power.
借债来维持政权
What do you expect from a country like this?
这样的国家 有什么指望
That's why we're going to overthrow Yuan,
正因为这样我们才要倒袁
overthrow this corrupt government,
推翻这个腐朽的统治
and build a new nation.
建立一个新的国家
No!
非也
Can China be saved by political revolution?
靠政治革命可以救中国
China's problems are accumulating.
中国的问题禾 积重难返
Can we solve the problems by changing people or governments?
靠换人换政府能解决吗
So according to you,
那照您这么说
our China has no way out?
我们中国岁不是没有出路了
There is a way, but the way out is not the old way.
有 但出路不是老路
The way out is a new way.
只有找到一条新路
China will not die.
中国才不会亡
What is the old way?
何谓老路
The dynastic cycle.
政权更选
The overthrow of an old dynasty,
推翻一个旧王朝
the establishment of a new dynasty.
建立一个新王朝
The cycle repeats itself. It's the old way.
循环往复 这是老路
And what is the new way?
那何为新路呢
Don't know.
不知道
That's what I'm looking for.
我正在找
Shouchang, I appreciate your knowledge and talent.
守常 我欣赏你的见识和才华
Will you look for this new path with me?
你愿意跟我一起找吗
To find a way to save China
为中国寻找一条救国之路
is my life's work.
乃是我李大钊毕生所求
I will.
我愿意
Good.
好
Zhongfu!
仲甫
You've both come here
你们俩都跑到这儿来了呀
and made us look for you!
让我们这通好找啊
Tickets... we have the tickets.
船票 船票拿到了
Tomorrow we can go back home.
明天我们就能回国了
Excellent. Finally we can go back.
太好了终于可以回去了
Zhongfu, before I go back,
仲甫啊 赶在回去之前
I finally got to see Shouchang.
可算把守常给见了
It's not in vain that you took
也不枉你白担了一回
the crime of being a traitor.
卖国贼的罪名啊
Not in vain... not in vain...
不柱 不柱
See me?
见我
Yeah.
是啊
He's here to see you today.
他今天可是专门来见你
Ever since he was on the "The Tiger",
自打他在《甲寅》上
and read your article,
看了你发表的文章之后
he's been wanting to see you.
就一直想要见你
It was worth the trip.
不虚此行
The harvest is very rich, such as the treasure.
收获甚丰 如获至宝
You... you always stay indoors and write articles
你呀 总是闷在屋子里写文章
not letting us care for you,
还不让我们管
nor letting us ask questions,
不让我们问
making yourself like a beggar.
把自己弄得跟个气丐似的
Unkept hair, dirty face, and body covered in lice.
蓬头垢面的 全身都是虱子
[Yi Baisha, styled Yuecun, famous thinker forced into exile in Japan for participating in the "Second Revolution" against Yuan Shikai]
[易白沙 字 越邨 著名思想家因参加讨伐袁世凯的"二次革命"被迫流亡日本]
You'll scare Junman back home!
回国不得吓着君曼啊
Hurry back!
赶紧回去
Cut your hair, take a bath, and change your clothes.
剪个头 洗个澡 换身衣服
There's a bath
澡可以洗
and there is only one change of clothes.
衣服只有一件没的换
Alright.
行了
Brother Zhongfu. Wait.
仲甫兄 等等
It's windy at sea. Take care of yourself.
海上风大 保重身体
Okay, then I'll be glad to do so.
好 那我就不客气了
Shouchang, I owe you three favours today.
守常 我今日欠你三个人情
In the future, you must remember to ask for them.
日后 你要记得讨要
What are they?
哪三个
One is to help me get out of trouble.
一 是帮我脱困
Second is to lend me clothes.
二 是借我衣服
And the third?
第三呢
I ate your food.
我蹭你的饭呀
But before I had enough to eat,
不过我还没吃饱
I was beaten away.
就把我打跑了
Then keep rubbing it in!
那就接着蹭呗
Can I buy you all dinner?
我请你们吃饭好不好
We haven't even eaten yet.
我们都没吃呢
Then we'll rub along.
那我们就跟着蹭
Good, Brother Zhongfu, this way.
好 仲甫兄 这边
Zhongfu, what time is it already, you're still not going to sleep?
仲甫 都几点了你还不睡觉
What is there worth seeing outside?
外边有什么可看的呀
The boat passed Shandong.
船过山东喽
I feel apprehensive as I near home.
近乡情
There's anger in my heart. I want to scold someone.
心中有气 想骂人
I want to scold Yuan Shikai.
想骂袁世凯
I also want to scold this Yuan Datou (=Silver coin engraved with Yuan's large head).
我也想骂这个袁大头
I don't know what he's thinking,
不知道他是怎么想的
he dared to give Qingdao to Japan.
就敢把青岛给了日本
You say, did this guy take the wrong medicine?
你说这斯是不是吃错药了
Yuan Shikai did not take the wrong medicine.
袁世凯没有吃错药
It's our country
是我们这国家
that is already incurable.
无药可治了
Why do you say that?
怎么讲
Think about it.
你想啊
Since Lin Zexu banned opium in the Daoguang era,
从道光年林则徐禁鸦片起
it's been seventy-five years.
整整七十五年了
In the middle of this, how many people
这中间有多少人
thought of different ways
想了多少输
but still couldn't save the Great Qing dynasty.
也没挽救一个大清王朝
Sun Yat-sen introduced the Republic from the West,
孙中山从西洋引进了共和制
people of the country all thought that this
国人也都以为这是一服
was a remedy to save the country and enrich the people.
可以救国富民的良药
Who would have thought, the republic works in other countries
谁曾想 这共和在外国灵
but inside of China it does not work anymore.
到了中国它就不灵了
After three or four years of the Republic,
共和三四年下来
the country is not as good as it used to be.
国家反倒不如以前了
Since there is no cure,
既然无药可治
then isn't taking the old way better.
那还是走老路顺当啊
These aren't the thoughts of just one or two people.
这可不是一个人两个人的想法
Baisha.
白沙
Isn't it?
可不是嘛
You said that Liang Shiyi's gang is now
你说 现在梁士诒这一帮人啊
jumping up and down in tandem everywhere,
到处串联 上蹄下跳
joining Master Yang Hu (=ROC Lieutenant General), Yan Jidao (=Yan Fu's alias)
就连杨虎公 严几道
also serving their tiger master to make a scene.
也为虎作伥瞎起哄
Unreasonable.
不可理喻
Yang Du, Yan Fu.
杨度 严复
They are the wisest who can have a momentary lapse in judgement,
那是聪明一世糊涂一时
whereas that Liang Shiyi group
而那个梁士诒一伙
are political hooligans with no moral bottom line.
则是没有道德底线的政治流氓
I made up a name for them
我给他们起了个名字
called Li Yilian. (lit. propriety, righteousness, honesty)
叫礼义廉
Li Yilian, what does this mean?
李易连 什么意思
Li Yilian, is shameless! (lit. propriety, righteousness, honesty, and a sense of shame; famous Chinese idiom)
礼义廉 无耻啊
Extremely shameless! Most shameless of all!
无耻至极 无耻之尤
Good! What a good Li Yilian!
好 好个礼义廉
Zhongfu, your thinking is clearly unusual!
仲甫 思想清奇呀
Baisha, I'm ashamed.
白沙 惭愧呀
For more than ten years,
十多年了
I, Chen Duxiu, first learned Kang Liang,
我陈独秀先学康梁
followed by [Sun] Yat-sen,
后随中山
committed to the political revolution,
致力政治革命
running this way and that way escaping death many times.
东奔西走 九死一生
Going to Japan alone for five times.
光日本就去了五次
As a result,
结果到现在
nothing is still achieved right?
不还是一事无成吗
China's affairs,
中国的事情
by relying on political revolution,
光靠政治革命
doesn't solve the fundamental problem.
解决不了根本问题
To get to the bottom of this, we must change our way of thinking.
追根溯源 要换换思路了
Do you have any new ideas?
你有什么新思想
I don't dare to say my new ideas.
新思想不敢说
On my return this time,
我这次回国
I've made up my mind.
打定主意了
For twenty years, I'm not going to touch politics.
二十年不谈政治
If you're not going to touch politics, then what do you want to do?
不谈政治你想干什么呀
Be reborn. Change one's body, change one's mind.
脱胎换骨 换人换脑子
It's not early anymore.
不早了
Hurry up and go to sleep.
赶快睡觉吧
Zhongfu, what time is it already?
仲甫 都几点了
What are you still sitting there for?
你还坐那儿干吗呀
It's so dark out there,
那外边黑漆麻乎的
you can't see anything at all.
什么也看不见
Sleep. Turn off the lights, okay?
睡觉 把灯关了 啊
I do see.
看得见
We, students,
吾辈学生
[Waseda University dormitory]
[日本早稻田大学宿舍]
especially among the people, should bear great responsibilities.
于国民中尤当负重大之责任
Those who study spiritual academics
研究精神上之学术者
should produce beautiful literature
宜时出其优美之文学
and noble thinking
高尚之思潮
to contribute to the spiritual development of our nation.
助我国民精神界之发展
Those who study material academics
研究物质上之学术者
should pay close attention to their profound thinking
宜时摅其湛深之思考
and apply them exquisitely
施以精巧之应用
to seek the development of our country's military technology and instruments.
谋我国军事工艺器械之发达
The spirit of sincerity is omnipotent,
诚以精神具万能之势力
and if held with sincerity and perseverance.
苟克持之以诚毅
one will have a great functional career.
将有伟大之功能事业
Based on the ignorance of conscience,
基于良知一念之微明
Cao Mo will avenge shame (cf. legend of General Cao Mo robbing Duke Huan of Qi)
则曹沫雪辱
and Goujian will take revenge, (cf. King Goujian of Yue's revenge on the state of Wu)
勾践复仇
when the time comes.
会有其时
Brother Fengzai, I say, you are really capable.
丰载兄 我说你可真行啊
Things are prepared so well!
东西备得可真全
This mahjong game, I really love playing!
这麻将啊 我最爱玩了
I also love playing!
我也爱玩
Brother Fengzai, you are truly wise and brilliant.
丰载兄 您真是英明神武啊
You unexpectedly got everyone ship tickets for a second class cabin.
竟然给大伙搞到了二等舱的船票
At the fourth class cabin, we
你说我们在四等舱
were laughing together with the poor.
跟那些穷哈哈在一起
That was so boring!
那多没意思啊
Right! So boring!
对 没意思啊
All of this doesn't mean much.
这都不算什么
My second uncle said
我二叔说了
Yuan Shikai wants to become an emperor.
袁世凯要当了皇帝
He's just the head of palace affairs.
他可就是大内总管
When you return home, help us do more publicity.
各位回国以后帮忙多做点宣传
In the future, I will surely not treat everyone unfairly.
将来一定不会亏待大家的
No problem!
没问题
Xifeng.
西风
I say, Brother Fengzai.
我说丰载兄
For the sake of Yuan Shikai,
哥几个可为了袁世凯
we don't even want to go study abroad.
这出国留学的名额都不要了
You have to tell Second Uncle about it, right?
怎么着你得跟二叔念切念切不是
I say,
我说
do all of you have this doubt?
你们是不是都有这个疑惑呀
Of course!
那是
Okay!
好
Then let me help you all dispel these doubts.
那我就帮你们来解解惑
My second uncle says,
我二叔说
as long as work is done,
只要事成了
we can all go to study at Beida (=Peking University).
让咱们都去北大上学
Are you serious?
真的假的
Then we will have boundless prospects.
那我们可就前途无量了
This is great! Beida!
太好了 北大呀
I was waiting for this sentence from you!
我就等你这句了
Zhongfu!
仲甫
Somebody made way for you,
人家给你让路
why did you not acknowledge them?
你怎么不理人家呀
This is unreasonable.
你这太不近人情了
Who is this person?
此人是谁呀
He is a famous Chinese United League veteran.
这是大名鼎鼎的同盟会元老
General Zou Yongcheng, commander of the Third Army of Hunan-Henan coalition forces.
湘豫联军的第三军军长邹永成将军
You need to give him an apology.
你得给人道个歉
I've always been uninterested in bureaucrats.
我素来对官優政客不感兴趣
Look at you!
你看你这人
Greetings Mr. Yi Baisha.
白沙先生好
[Zou Yongcheng, styled Qizhi, Chinese United League member]
[邹永成 字 器之 同盟会会员]
Greetings General Zou.
邹将军好
Mr. Zhongfu
仲甫先生
General Zou isn't an ordinary official.
邹将军可不是一般的官员
In the second year or the Republic, Song Jiaoren was killed.
民国二年宋教仁被杀
General Zou deeply felt that the Republic would fall apart.
邹将军深感共和国将成为泡影
He left a suicide poem,
留绝命诗一首
jumped into the Huangpu River in anger and attempted suicide.
愤然跳进黄浦江自杀
"After more than ten years of revolution,
轰轰革命十余年
Hu Lu (=Xiongnu, a.k.a ruling Manchus of Qing) was expelled from their ancestral whip.
驱逐胡虏着祖鞭
Only to find that the ape (=Yuan) somersaulted out,
不料猿猴筋斗出
the Republic became a dream and I returned to Heaven."
共和成梦我归天
How noble and majestic!
多么浩气磅礴呀
Not really, my humble self is a simple man.
哪里 在下无能啊
Jumping into Huangpu River to commit suicide.
投黄浦江自杀
Just an attempt?
未遂呀
Indeed, it was an attempt.
的确是未遂
Luckily rescued by fishermen.
幸得渔民救起
If so,
若是如此
I actually think you are a fool.
我倒觉得你是个糊涂人
How can a revolutionary kill himself so easily?
革命者怎能轻生自杀
I, Chen Duxiu, in this life,
我陈独秀此生
would never do anything stupid to kill myself for the revolution.
绝不会做自绝于革命的蠢事
Zhongfu!
仲甫
General Zou, I apologize.
邹将军 抱歉啊
It's alright.
没关系 没关系
Zhongfu!
仲甫
You were too overbearing.
你太霸道了
Being ruthless does not make you a true hero.
无情未必真豪杰
Maybe one day,
没准哪一天
I will also be like Qu Yuan,
我也会像屈原一样
jumping into a river to commit suicide.
投江自尽的
At that time, will you also come ridicule me?
你到时候也来嘲笑我吗
Sorry, Baisha.
对不起白沙
I'm not in a good mood, I forgot my manners.
我心情不好 失态了
Forgive me.
请原谅
Junman is coughing up blood.
君曼咳血了
At a young age, you can get tuberculosis.
年纪轻轻就得了痨病
Yannian, Qiaonian, those two unfilial sons
延年乔年那两个逆子
were not at home taking care of their mother
不在家侍母
and recently ran to Shanghai.
最近也跑到上海去了
Pity her, she is both an aunt and a stepmother,
可怜她既是姨妈又是继母
sick and with no money,
生病又没钱
in one family with five to six mouths.
一家五六口
I really don't know
我真不知道
how they survive.
他们该怎么生活
You... This way of managing the family is questionable
你呀这治家的方式也值得商耀
I heard you insist on not giving
听说你坚持不给
living expenses to the two brothers Yannian and Qiaonian.
延年乔年两兄弟生活费
But leting them work while studying,
让他们勤工俭学
providing for themselves,
自己养活自己
at a young age.
小小年纪
Who can take this kind of suffering?
哪吃得了这样的苦啊
Why can't they take this kind of suffering?
为什么吃不了这个苦
If I had money I still wouldn't give it.
有钱也不给
Besides, I don't have money.
况且我没钱
[Shanghai French Concession Handling Station]
[上海法租界搬运站]
Careful, brother!
小心啊哥
Come!
来
[Chen Yannian, eldest son of Chen Duxiu]
[陈延年 陈独秀长子]
[Chen Qiaonian, second son of Chen Duxiu]
[陈乔年 陈独秀次子]
Come!
来
Here!
这
Gloomy men, let's sing a tune! Heiyo!
男忧愁来唱曲子 嘿哟
Gloomy women, come snivel! Heiyo!
女忧愁来哭鼻子 嘿哟
If there's any matter, then sing!
有什么事来唱
You old thing!
你这个老东西
This old thing!
你这老东西
You can't even carry one bag, you still want to carry two?
一袋抬不了 你还抬两袋
Spilling beans all over the ground!
满地撒豆子
You idler!
你这磨洋工啊
If you can then do it. If you can't then get out of here!
能干就干不能干给我滚蛋
I'll beat you to death! Let you be an idler
我打死你让你磨洋工
Let you be an idler! Let you...
让你磨洋工 让你
Still hitting?
还打人
What are you doing!
干什么
Don't move!
别动
Don't move! What are you doing!
别动干什么
What do you want!
干什么
For what reason are you hitting someone?
凭什么打人啊
Are you okay?
没事吧
For what reason...
凭什么
Because I'm in charge here!
凭这儿我说了算
Hey! How come it's you again?
怎么又是你这小子啊
Did you want to take the whipping for him?
是不是想替他埃鞭子了
Get out of here for me!
给我滚蛋
His leg already had an injury
他腿本来就有伤
What's wrong if the things fell on the ground?
东西掉地上怎么了
Isn't it fine if it's picked up
捡起来不就行了吗
What the fuck does his injury have to do with me!
有伤关我屁事啊
You have to take responsibility for delaying business!
耽误了工期你负责啊
But you still can't beat someone up!
那你也不能打人啊
I just did. So what?
我就打了怎么样啊
Believe it or not I'll beat both of you together
信不信我连你一起打
What are you doing?
干什么
Don't hit!
别动手
You can't fight!
不许打
Want to rebel, is that right?
想造反是吧
You are quite a righteous brat, huh?
你小子挺仗义啊
Fine, today I'll let you handle this first issue.
行我今天就让你管一次事
Old Jia's life, you take care of.
老贾的活你来干
All of you can't get involved.
你们都别掺和啊
Whoever comes out will do it themselves.
谁出头谁干
Come!
来
I'll do it.
我干
Me too.
还有我
Count me in!
算我一个
Since you two volunteered, you two do it.
就你俩出头你俩干
Come!
来
No more nonsense!
别废话了
Who's next? Break it up!
好该谁了 散了散了
What are you still looking at? Scatter!
还看什么看散了散了散了
Turn over these two.
翻个面
It's nothing, all of you go back to work!
没事都干活去
Grab here.
抓着这儿
Okay.
好
Here!
来
Lift
上
All right all right. Go do your job.
行了行了干自己活去
What are you being distracted for!
愣什么你
Pick up those beans cleanly for me.
把豆子给我捡干净
If you miss even one grain, I'll kill you.
少捡一粒我弄死你
Quickly!
麻利点
Hurry up!
快点
Older brother.
哥
I can't hold on anymore.
不行了
Hurry and put it down! Don't injure your waist.
你快放下 别伤着腰啊
That's not it, my waistband broke.
不是我裤腰带断了
Well then...
那这
Put your legs together!
你腿并上
Don't move, alright.
别动弹啊
What are you messing around for? Quickly!
磨蹭什么呢麻利点
Take your legs out.
抽腿
Put on your shoes.
把鞋穿上
You don't even want your shoes on now, huh?
鞋也不穿了啊
Let go! Let go!
松手 松手
Let go of me.
放开我
What's going on?
干什么
You guys can't be like this!
你们不能这样
Stop right now! What do you guys want to do!
快住手你们这是干什么呀
Let go. Let go of me!
放手 放开我
Get your hands off of me!
你们把手松开
What are you guys doing!
你们干什么
You can't be like this!
不能这样
Let go of me!
放开我
What are you doing
干什么
They're hurting someone!
伤着人了
That's a girl!
那是个女孩子
What are you doing?
干什么呀
Let go! Let go!
放开放开
Hands off! Take your hands off right now!
松手快松手
What the heck is going on down there?
今天这是发生什么事了
Throw them overboard at portside!
棒打鸳鸯海上西厢
Let me go!
放开我
Out of the way
让开
Stop fighting
别打了
Who!
谁
Who did it?
谁干的
Who threw it?
谁扔的
What are you guys doing?
你们在干什么
Do you want to steal money or jump into the sea and run away?
是要盗取钱财还是准备跳海逃跑
Our boat tickets were stolen!
我们船票被偷了
We just arrived on deck!
才到甲板上来的
Don't hit!
别动手
Just forget it!
算了吧
Let go!
放开
Stop fighting!
别打了
Good!
好好好
Stop the ruckus!
别吵了别吵了
It's forbidden to make a ruckus here.
这里禁止喧
We are on the ocean.
这里是海上
This boat belongs to Japan.
这是属于日本的船
People who don't have a boat ticket must buy one.
没有船票的人必须购票
So, everyone don't misunderstand
所以大家别误会
We conducted an investigation in secret
我们秘密进行了调查
and found out that those two originally did not have boat tickets,
发现那二位根本没有船票
therefore
因此
these two must buy boat tickets.
他们二位必须买票
Let these two youths off.
你放过这两个青年
The boat tickets, I'll pay for them.
船票我来付
Okay as long as the tickets are purchased, it's fine.
好只要补票就行
It's not okay! You guys...
不行你们几个
You have to apologize to these two Chinese youngsters.
要向这两个中国年轻人道
This is our Japanese ocean liner,
这是我们日本的轮船
we are carrying out official business.
我们是在执行公务
There is no reason to apologize, you guys better not go too far.
没有理由道你们不要太过分
Is beating people carrying out official business?
打人是执行公务吗
Is humiliating a woman carrying out official business?
每辱妇女是执行公务吗
Is taking off a girl's clothes carrying out official business?
脱女人衣服是执行公务吗
I'm telling you guys...
我告诉你们
you Japanese people are abusing your power,
你们日本人滥用职权
wantonly insulting us Chinese people.
肆意厚骂我们中国人
This is an insult to our China!
就是对我们中国的悔辱
This is international waters!
这里是公海
This is
这是一件
a big matter that is enough to cause an international incident.
足以引起国际纠纷的大事情
Will you stop
你们非要
messing around before this matter gets out of hand?
把这件事闹得不可收拾吗
Apologize!
道歉
Apologize! Apologize!
道歉 道歉
Apologize! Apologize! Apologize! Bad guys, apologize!
道歉 道歉 道歉 坏人道歉
Okay! I got it!
好 我知道了
You two quickly apologize.
你俩快道歉
Sorry. Sorry.
对不起 对不起
Hey, let's go!
喂 我们走
We won!
我们赢了
This is the victory? What was the victory?
这就赢了 赢什么了呀
The three words "I am sorry", and it's over?
对不起三个字就完事了
That's right!
就是
Does this count as victory?
这算赢吗
Keep fighting!
接着打呗
Come back and keep fighting!
回来接着打
What are you saying!
说什么呢
Are you still human?
还是人吗你
Seeing your fellow citizen being bullied...
看到自己同胞受欺负
not coming out to lend a hand...
不出手相助
instead, you are on the side making sarcastic remarks.
反而在旁边说风凉话
Are you still Chinese?
你们还是中国人吗
Do still know what shame is?
还知不知道什么是羞耻
You know what shame is,
您知道羞耳啊
what's the point of showing off here?
在这儿能算什么本事呀
If you have the ability fight a battle in Europe,
有能耐到欧洲打仗去
you would exterminate the Eight-Nation Alliance.
把八国联军给灭了
That's right!
就是
That's what is called ability.
那才叫本事
You!
你
What do you want to do?
干什么 干什么
A Chinese people fighting each other
中国人打中国人
Come
来来来
Let foreigners properly see...
让外国人好好看看
how Chinese people bully each other
中国人是怎么欺负中国人的
Come
来来来
Do you see it?
看到了吗
Chinese people are bullying each other!
中国人欺负中国人了
Come  Everyone come see
来大家看一看
Stop quarrelling, all of you go back for me
别吵 都给我回去
Let's go
走走走
All of you go back
都回去
Don't be angry, don't lower yourself to their level
别生气 别跟他们一般见识
Make way
让一下
Raise your feet a little
高指一下贵脚
You stepped on my tile
踩着我牌了
What tile?
什么牌呀
Little... Little chick it seems like
么幺鸡好像是吧
This eyesight of yours is not good
你这眼神也不行啊
It's a cake
是一饼
Play often?
常玩
Why did you throw the tile!
怎么把牌扔了
Fellow citizens being insulted
同胞受辱
is far less important
就远没有
than your mahjong game, is it?
比你们打麻将重要是吗
What does this hell does have to do with playing Mahjong!
这跟打麻将有啥关系
What did you throw my tile for?
扔我牌干吗
How can they be justified in taking tickets?
他们逃票还有理了呀
The reason why the country is not prospering...
国之所以不昌
is that the people's wisdom is not yet open.
在于民智未开也
Meaning?!
至于吗
Playing mahjong...
打麻将跟国昌不昌
What does it matter whether the people are open or not?
民开不开有什么关系
What did you throw my tiles for?
扔我麻将干吗
You guys still want to lose face?
你们还不嫌丢人哪
Us Chinese people arguing amongst ourselves here...
我们中国人在这儿自己吵架
We let the foreigners see a joke
让外国人在这儿看笑话
Everyone else, go back to your cabin. Right now
所有人回船舱去马上
Let's go
走
Mr. Zhongfu, are you alright?
仲甫先生 没事吧
I'm alright
没事
General Yongcheng
永成将军
My discourteousness from before
我为之前对你的失礼
I formally apologize to you
正式向你道
You are a fellow
您是一条汉子
Thank you sirs
谢谢几位先生
Sir,
这位先生
The boat ticket money...
那个船票钱
We will for sure return it to you as soon as possible
我们一定会尽快还给您的
No need no need
不用不用不用
We are all Chinese people
大家都是中国人
Helping each other is what we should do
帮助是应该的
Thank you
谢谢
Mr. Zhongfu.
仲甫先生
Your help, despite what happened yesterday,
您不计昨日之嫌出手相助
I wholeheartedly thank you
心刚谢谢您
What about the events of yesterday?
哪来的昨日之嫌呀
You forgot
您忘了
At Waseda,
在早稻田的时候
I spit a mouthful on you
我吐了您一口
How about if I didn't forget
没忘又如何
spitting back at you
吐还你
You spit a mouthful of phlegm on me
你吐我一口痰
it's your bravery
是你的血性
Today's fight...
今日我们打这一架
is our bravery
是我们的血性
But it's only by bravery
但是仅凭血性
This fight is going to last until when?
这架要打到什么时候啊
The principles in this, do you understand?
这其中的道理你懂吗
I will wholeheartedly listen to your instructions
心刚愿听先生教询
Good
好
Then let's go inside the cabins to chat
那我们去我船舱里面聊聊吧
General Yongcheng, please
永成将军 请
Let's go.   Come.
走来
Qiaonian
乔年
Good  Now I won't be afraid of it falling
行这回不怕它掉了
Here
给
Brother Yannian, Brother Qiaonian!
延年哥 乔年哥哥
What are you doing here?
你怎么来了 你怎么来了
What good food are you eating?
你们在吃什么好吃的
I also want to eat!
我也要吃
[Chen Zimei, daughter of Chen Duxiu]
[陈子美 陈独秀女儿]
Aunt!
姨妈
Yannian, Qiaonian.
延年乔年
So hard to eat!
好难吃
What's wrong Zimei?
怎么了子美
Don't eat this anymore.
不吃这个了
Aunt brought over some buns for you guys.
姨妈给你们带了包子
It just came out of the boiler.
刚出锅的
Eat the buns.
吃包子
Aunt, we won't eat it.
姨妈我们不吃
Aunt is not an foreigner.
姨妈又不是外人
What is it that you can't eat.
有什么不能吃的
You eat it
你吃吧
Thank you aunt
谢谢姨妈
I brought you guys egg soup
我给你们带了鸡蛋汤
Here
来
Fresh out of the pot
刚出锅的
Thank you aunt
谢谢姨妈
Yannian. Come, eat some buns
延年来吃包子
Aunt, money is used to buy this
姨妈这也是拿钱买的
When you look at it, it doesn't look good. Once you eat it, it's quite flavorful
看着不好看吃起来挺香的
Where's Henian
鹤年呢
He's not feeling very well
他不太舒服
I had a neighbour help look after him
我让邻居帮忙看着了
Yannian, Qiaonian
延年 乔年，
Aunt has come here many times to urge you guys...
姨妈这么多次来劝你们
You guys are always stubbornly not willing to come home with me
你们总是着不肯跟我回家
Your father is about to come back
现在你们爸爸要回来了
Come home with aunt
跟姨妈回家吧
We won't go back
我们是不会回去的
We don't have anything to do with this person
我们跟这人没有任何关系
But you guys working outside like this...
可你们这样在外边打工
is truly a lot of hardship
实在是太苦了
Can't even get hot food to eat
连口热的都吃不上
Come home with me
跟我回去
Good or bad, you can eat something hot
好罗能吃上口热的
Okay?
好吧
Aunt, don't try to persuade us anymore
姨妈 您就别劝了
We will rely on ourselves
我们就是要靠自己
This is our principle
这是我们的原则
Zimei
子美
Your brothers are going to go to work
哥哥们得去干活了
This time we can't accompany you to play
这回就不陪你玩了
Next time, okay
下回啊
Let's go
走吧
Goodbye aunt
姨妈再见
Wait a minute
等会儿 等会儿
Here
来
Take these all of these buns
把包子都拿上
Older brother, you agreed that I would send you my grasshopper
哥哥 你答应过我要送我螺的
Brother promised you, I will do it for sure
哥哥答应你的一定做到